INSTRUCTOR: This is a 3.
It's sloppily written and
rendered at an extremely low
resolution of 28-by-28 pixels.
But your brain has no trouble
recognizing it as a three.
And I want you to take
a moment to appreciate
how crazy it is that brains
can do this so effortlessly.
I mean, this, this and this are
also recognizable as 3's, even
though the specific
values of each pixel
is very different from
one image to the next.
The particular light
sensitive cells
in your eye that are firing
when you see this three
are very different from the
ones firing when you see this 3.
But something in that crazy,
smart visual cortex of yours
resolves these as
representing the same idea,
while at the same time
recognizing other images
as their own distinct ideas.
But if I told you, hey, sit down
and write for me a program that
takes in a grid of 28-by-28
pixels like this and outputs
a single number
between 0 and 10,
telling you what it
thinks the digit is, well,
the task goes from comically
trivial to dauntingly difficult.
Unless you've been
living under a rock,
I think I hardly need to
motivate the relevance
and importance of machine
learning and neural networks
to the present
and to the future.
But what I want
to do here is show
you what a neural
network actually
is, assuming no
background, and to help
visualize what it's
doing, not as a buzzword,
but as a piece of math.
My hope is just that you come
away feeling like the structure
itself is motivated and to feel
what it means when you read
or you hear about a neural
network, quote unquote,
"learning."
This video is just going to
be devoted to the structure
component of that,
and the following one
is going to tackle learning.
What we're going to
do is put together
a neural network that can learn
to recognize handwritten digits.
This is a somewhat
classic example
for introducing the topic.
And I'm happy to stick
with the status quo
here because at the
end of the two videos,
I want to point you to
a couple good resources
where you can learn more
and where you can download
the code that does this and play
with it on your own computer.
There are many, many
variants of neural networks.
And in recent years, there's
been sort of a boom in research
towards these variants.
But in these two
introductory videos,
you and I are just going to look
at the simplest plain vanilla
form with no added frills.
This is kind of a
necessary prerequisite
for understanding any of the
more powerful modern variants.
And trust me, it still has
plenty of complexity for us
to wrap our minds around.
But even in this
simplest form, it
can learn to recognize
handwritten digits, which
is a pretty cool thing for
a computer to be able to do.
And at the same
time, you'll see how
it does fall short of a couple
hopes that we might have for it.
As the name suggests,
neural networks
are inspired by the brain.
But let's break that down.
What are the neurons?
And in what sense are
they linked together?
Now, when I say neuron, all
I want you to think about
is a thing that holds a
number, specifically a number
between 0 and 1.
It's really not more than that.
For example, the network
starts with a bunch
of neurons corresponding
to each of the 28 times
28 pixels of the input image,
which is 784 neurons in total.
Each one of these
holds a number that
represents the grayscale value
of the corresponding pixel,
ranging from 0 for black pixels
up to 1 for white pixels.
This number inside the neuron
is called its activation.
And the image you
might have in mind
here is that each neuron is
lit up when its activation is
a high number.
So all of these
784 neurons make up
the first layer of our network.
Now jumping over
to the last layer,
this has 10 neurons, each
representing one of the digits.
The activation in these
neurons, again, some number
that's between 0 and
1 represents how much
the system thinks that a given
image corresponds with a given
digit.
There's also a couple
layers in between called
the hidden layers, which,
for the time being,
should just be a giant
question mark for how
on Earth this process
of recognizing digits
is going to be handled.
In this network, I
chose two hidden layers,
each one with 16 neurons.
And admittedly, that's kind
of an arbitrary choice.
To be honest, I chose
two layers based
on how I want to motivate the
structure in just a moment.
And 16, well, that
was just a nice number
to fit on the screen.
In practice, there
is a lot of room
for experiment with the
specific structure here.
The way the network operates,
activations in one layer
determine the activations
of the next layer.
And of course, the heart of
the network as an information
processing mechanism
comes down to exactly how
those activations from one
layer bring about activations
in the next layer.
It's meant to be
loosely analogous to how
in biological
networks of neurons,
some groups of neurons firing
cause certain others to fire.
Now the network I'm
showing here has already
been trained to
recognize digits.
And let me show you
what I mean by that.
It means if you feed
in an image lighting up
all 784 neurons of
the input layer,
according to the brightness
of each pixel in the image,
that pattern of
activations causes
some very specific pattern
in the next layer, which
causes some pattern in the one
after it, which finally gives
some pattern in
the output layer.
And the brightest neuron
of that output layer
is the network's choice,
so to speak, for what
digit this image represents.
And before jumping into the math
for how one layer influences
the next or how
training works, let's
just talk about why
it's even reasonable
to expect a layered
structure like this
to behave intelligently.
What are we expecting here?
What is the best hope for
what those middle layers might
be doing?
Well, when you or
I recognize digits,
we piece together
various components.
A 9 has a loop up top
and a line on the right.
An 8 also has a loop
up top, but it's paired
with another loop down low.
A 4 basically breaks down into
three specific lines and things
like that.
Now, in a perfect
world, we might
hope that each neuron in
the second to last layer
corresponds with one of these
subcomponents, that any time you
feed in an image with, say, a
loop up top like a 9 or an 8,
there's some specific
neuron whose activation
is going to be close to 1.
And I don't mean this
specific loop of pixels.
The hope would be that any
generally loopy pattern
towards the top sets
off this neuron.
That way, going from the third
layer to the last one just
requires learning which
combination of subcomponents
corresponds to which digits.
Of course, that just kicks
the problem down the road
because how would you
recognize these subcomponents
or even learn what the right
subcomponents should be.
And I still haven't
even talked about how
one layer influences the next.
But run with me on
this one for a moment.
Recognizing a loop can also
break down into subproblems.
One reasonable way
to do this would
be to first recognize the
various little edges that
make it up.
Similarly, a long
line, like the kind
you might see in the
digits 1 or 4 or 7, well,
that's really just a
long edge, or maybe you
think of it as a certain pattern
of several smaller edges.
So maybe our hope is that each
neuron in the second layer
of the network corresponds with
the various relevant little
edges.
Maybe when an image
like this one comes in,
it lights up all of
the neurons associated
with around 8 to 10
specific little edges, which
in turn lights up the
neurons associated
with the upper loop and
a long vertical line,
and those light up the
neuron associated with a 9.
Whether or not this is what
our final network actually does
is another question, one
that I'll come back to once
we see how to train the network.
But this is a hope
that we might have,
a sort of goal with the
layered structure like this.
Moreover, you can
imagine how being
able to detect edges
and patterns like this
would be really useful for
other image recognition tasks.
And even beyond
image recognition,
there are all sorts
of intelligent things
you might want to do that break
down into layers of abstraction.
Parsing speech, for example,
involves taking raw audio
and picking out
distinct sounds, which
combine to make certain
syllables, which combine
to form words, which combine
to make up phrases and more
abstract thoughts, et cetera.
But getting back to how
any of this actually works,
picture yourself
right now designing
how exactly the
activations in one layer
might determine the
activations in the next.
The goal is to have some
mechanism that could conceivably
combine pixels into edges or
edges into patterns or patterns
into digits.
And to zoom in on one
very specific example,
let's say the hope is
for one particular neuron
in the second layer to pick up
on whether or not the image has
an edge in this region here.
The question at hand
is, what parameters
should the network have?
What dials and
knobs should you be
able to tweak so that
it's expressive enough
to potentially
capture this pattern
or any other pixel pattern or
the pattern that several edges
can make, a loop and
other such things?
Well, what we'll do
is assign a weight
to each one of the
connections between our neuron
and the neurons from
the first layer.
These weights are just numbers.
Then take all of those
activations from the first layer
and compute their weighted sum,
according to these weights.
I find it helpful to
think of these weights
as being organized into a
little grid of their own.
And I'm going to
use green pixels
to indicate positive
weights and red pixels
to indicate negative
weights, where
the brightness of that pixel
is some loose depiction
of the weights value.
Now, if we made the weights
associated with almost all
of the pixels 0 except for some
positive weights in this region
that we care about, then
taking the weighted sum of all
the pixel values
really just amounts
to adding up the
values of the pixel
just in the region
that we care about.
And if you really
wanted to pick up
on whether there's an edge
here, what you might do
is have some negative weights
associated with the surrounding
pixels.
Then the sum is largest when
those middle pixels are bright,
but the surrounding
pixels are darker.
When you compute a
weighted sum like this,
you might come out
with any number.
But for this
network, what we want
is for activations to be
some value between 0 and 1.
So a common thing to do is
to pump this weighted sum
into some function that
squishes the real number line
into the range between 0 and 1.
And a common function
that does this
is called the sigmoid function,
also known as a logistic curve.
Basically, very negative
inputs end up close to 0,
very positive inputs
end up close to 1,
and it just steadily
increases around the input 0.
So the activation
of the neuron here
is basically a measure of how
positive the relevant weighted
sum is.
But maybe it's not that you
want the neuron to light up
when the weighted
sum is bigger than 0.
Maybe you only want it to be
active when the sum is bigger
than, say, 10.
That is, you want some
bias for it to be inactive.
What we'll do then is just
add in some other number
like negative 10 to
this weighted sum
before plugging it through
the sigmoid squishification
function.
That additional number
is called the bias.
So the weights tell you what
pixel pattern this neuron
in the second layer
is picking up on.
And the bias tells you
how high the weighted sum
needs to be before
the neuron starts
getting meaningfully active.
And that is just one neuron.
Every other neuron
in this layer is
going to be connected
to all 784 pixel neurons
from the first layer.
And each one of
those 784 connections
has its own weight
associated with it.
Also, each one has some
bias, some other number
that you add on to
the weighted sum
before squishing it
with the sigmoid.
And that's a lot to think about.
With this hidden
layer of 16 neurons,
that's a total of 784 times 16
weights along with 16 biases.
And all of that is just the
connections from the first layer
to the second.
The connections between
the other layers
also have a bunch of weights
and biases associated with them.
All said and done, this network
has almost exactly 13,000 total
weights and biases, 13,000 knobs
and dials that can be tweaked
and turned to make this network
behave in different ways.
So when we talk about
learning, what that's
referring to is
getting the computer
to find a valid setting for all
of these many, many numbers,
so that it'll actually
solve the problem at hand.
One thought experiment
that is at once fun
and kind of horrifying is to
imagine sitting down and setting
all of these weights
and biases by hand,
purposefully tweaking the
numbers so that the second layer
picks up on edges,
the third layer
picks up on patterns, et cetera.
I personally find this
satisfying rather than
just treating the network
as a total black box,
because when the network doesn't
perform the way you anticipate,
if you've built up a little
bit of a relationship with what
those weights and
biases actually mean,
you have a starting place for
experimenting with how to change
the structure to improve.
Or when the network
does work, but not
for the reasons
you might expect,
digging into what the
weights and biases are doing
is a good way to
challenge your assumptions
and really expose the full
space of possible solutions.
By the way, the actual function
here is a little cumbersome
to write down, don't you think?
So let me show you a more
notationally compact way
that these connections
are represented.
This is how you'd see
it if you choose to read
up more about neural networks.
Organize all of the
activations from one layer
into a column as a vector.
Then organize all of
the weights as a matrix,
where each row of that
matrix corresponds
to the connections
between one layer
and a particular neuron
in the next layer.
What that means is that
taking the weighted sum
of the activations
in the first layer,
according to these
weights, corresponds
to one of the terms
in the matrix vector
product of everything we
have on the left here.
By the way, so much of
machine learning just
comes down to having a good
grasp of linear algebra.
So for any of you who want
a nice visual understanding
for matrices and what matrix
vector multiplication means,
take a look at the series I did
on linear algebra, especially
chapter 3.
Back to our expression,
instead of talking
about adding the bias to
each one of these values
independently, we represent it
by organizing all those biases
into a vector and
adding the entire vector
to the previous
matrix vector product.
Then as a final step, I'll wrap
a sigmoid around the outside
here.
And what that's
supposed to represent
is that you're going to
apply the sigmoid function
to each specific component of
the resulting vector inside.
So once you write down this
weight matrix and these vectors
as their own symbols, you can
communicate the full transition
of activations from
one layer to the next
in an extremely tight and
neat little expression.
And this makes the relevant
code both a lot simpler
and a lot faster since many
libraries optimize the heck out
of matrix multiplication.
Remember how earlier
I said, these neurons
are simply things
that hold numbers?
Well, of course, the specific
numbers that they hold
depends on the
image you feed in.
So it's actually more accurate
to think of each neuron
as a function, one that
takes in the outputs of all
the neurons in
the previous layer
and spits out a number
between 0 and 1.
Really, the entire
network is just
a function, one that takes
in 784 numbers as an input
and spits out 10
numbers as an output.
It's an absurdly
complicated function,
one that involves 13,000
parameters in the forms of these
weights and biases that pick up
on certain patterns and which
involves iterating many matrix
vector products and the sigmoid
squishification function.
But it's just a
function nonetheless.
And in a way, it's
kind of reassuring
that it looks complicated.
I mean, if it were
any simpler, what hope
would we have that it could take
on the challenge of recognizing
digits?
And how does it take
on that challenge?
How does this network learn the
appropriate weights and biases
just by looking at data?
Well, that's what I'll
show in the next video.
And I'll also dig a
little more into what
this particular network
we're seeing is really doing.
Now is the point I suppose
I should say subscribe
to stay notified about when
that video or any new videos
come out.
But realistically, most
of you don't actually
receive notifications
from YouTube, do you?
Maybe more, honestly,
I should say subscribe,
so that the neural networks
that underlie YouTube's
recommendation
algorithm are primed
to believe that you want to
see content from this channel
get recommended to you.
Anyway, stay posted for more.
Thank you very much to everyone
supporting these videos
on Patreon.
I've been a little
slow to progress
in the probability
series this summer,
but I'm jumping back into
it after this project.
So Patrons, you can look
out for updates there.
To close things off
here, I have with me
Lisha Lee, who did her PhD
work on the theoretical side
of deep learning
and who currently
works at a venture capital firm
called Amplify Partners, who
kindly provided some of
the funding for this video.
So, Lisha, one thing I think
we should quickly bring up
is this sigmoid function.
As I understand
it, early networks
use this to squish the
relevant weighted sum
into that interval
between 0 and 1,
kind of motivated by this
biological analogy of neurons
either being inactive or active.
LISHA LEE: Exactly.
INSTRUCTOR: But relatively
few modern networks
actually use sigmoid anymore.
That's kind of
old school, right?
LISHA LEE: Or rather, ReLU seems
to be much easier to train.
INSTRUCTOR: And ReLU--
ReLU stands for
Rectified Linear Unit.
LISHA LEE: Yes, it's
this kind of function
where you're just taking
a max of 0 and a, where
a is given by what you were
explaining in the video.
And what this was sort
of motivated from,
I think was partially
by a biological analogy
with how neurons would
either be activated or not.
And so if it passes
a certain threshold,
it would be the
identity function.
But if it did not, then it
would just not be activated.
So it'd be 0.
So it's kind of
a simplification.
Using sigmoids
didn't help training,
or it was very difficult
to train at some point.
And people just tried ReLU.
And it happened to work very
well for these incredibly deep
neural networks.
INSTRUCTOR: All right.
Thank you, LIsha.